A while back, we went over the clinical
evidence indicating that fish oil and
more specifically omega-3s positively
impact your brain. In that analysis, we
went over six or seven studies largely
indicating that long-term exposure to
omega-3s improve cognitive performance,
especially memory, if I remember
correctly. Maybe I need some more
omega-3s. Anyway, I'd like to introduce
you to several ways that omega-3 fats
affect your brain. All of which are not
anything I've ever seen discussed
before, like ephox, synapsins, and more.
In brief, if you're not familiar with
omega-3s, they're polyunsaturated fats,
which means that they have multiple
kinks in a normally straight chain of
carbon atoms like insaturated fat. These
specific polyunsaturated fats can be
consumed from fatty fish, fish oil,
krill oil supplements, or as well as uh
algae oil, at least the ones that we're
concerned with. Uh since omega-3s come
in different forms. So, what happens to
your brain when you consume a fish oil
supplement or otherwise? We're going to
rely on these two scientific reviews.
The first way omega-3s affect your brain
is through the production of teased
eoxes. These are, and this sounds so
nerdy, electrofphilic fatty acid oxo
derivatives. Okay, to simplify, normally
enzymes in your cells called cylo
oxygenases and lipoo oxygenases produce
pro-inflammatory molecules called
icosenoids. But fascinatingly, when they
interact with omega-3 fats, they convert
omega-3s to ephoxes. Now, ephoxes can be
produced by the cells in the brain. And
when they're produced, they're often
kicked out of the cell and then they can
bind to immune cells in the brain called
microga. Now, when there's
neuroinflammation, meaning that micro ga
are abundant and activated called an M1
phase by older immunology terms, these
cells can do damage to their
surroundings because they can release
varying pro-inflammatory molecules that
cause stress to the surrounding cells in
the brain like the various neurons and
support cells like aststerytes. Yet when
ephoxes bind these M1 activated microg
GA they can convince them to become M2
or less activated. Functionally that
means that the cells become focused on
cleaning the brain, clearing debris,
promoting repair instead of attacking
perceived threats. Ephes are able to do
that by entering the micro GA passively
and binding to a potent master protein
called pargamma. Par gamma can move into
the cell's nucleus and change gene
expression as in which genes are
transcribed to become proteins. So
instead of genes like inos interlucan 1
beta and other pro-inflammatory
molecules, it'll encourage more M2 style
genes like ARG1 and uh an
anti-inflammatory molecule interlucan
10. What's cool about this mechanism is
that par gamma is usually bound to
varying molecules to activate or
inactivate it. and ephoxes are not
believed to be one that it usually binds
to. So, it's really just a mimicking of
the molecules that leads to this
positive effect, which I think is so
cool. Okay, you still with me? If that
wasn't interesting to you, totally
respect it. But it's about to get a heck
of a lot more detailed on some of these
other mechanisms.
So, the door's over there. If you're
along for the ride, let's get into the
second mechanism. You remember that par
gamma binding by EOX? Well, omega-3s
even before being converted to
Ephso bind par. One of the advantages of
creating more binding with PAR gamma is
also the bullying that PAR does. In your
cells, you have this potent
pro-inflammatory mechanism mediated by a
master lethal protein called NFCappa B.
If this protein, this complex is
activated in the cytool of your cells,
it'll travel inside the nucleus where
your genes are kept there. It'll target
binding pro-inflammatory genes to
generate those pro-inflammatory proteins
that we discussed. Luckily, PAR gamma
when activated by something like
omega-3s or its derivatives will
sequester the activating proteins of
NFCappa beta essentially stealing the
keys to the car. Even cooler though,
this same binding of omega-3s to PAR
gamma leads to something called a
post-transational modification where the
protein has a tag attached to it. In
this case, PAR is sumoilated, meaning a
small ubiquitin protein is attached to
it. Sumoilated PAR allows PAR to bind
co-pressors of NFCappa B, meaning it'll
pick up hitchhikers that hate NFCappa B
and carry them into the nucleus to bind
NFCappa B genes. And when NFCappa B
tries to bind, it can't because par and
its co-pressors are blocking it. Like I
said, par gamma bullies NFCappa B. But
then again, NFCappa B is a vicious when
it's overactive. Okay, those are just
some of the ways that omega-3s influence
pars. But let's get into another maybe
my favorite mechanism. The reality is
that there are many, many more
mechanisms I haven't seen anyone
describe before, like long-term
potentiation, stem cell activation, and
more. I'm going to be covering much more
in the extended version of this video
that you're watching. If you're
interested in nerding out beyond the
ones that uh we're going to be about to
go over, check out the Physionic
Insiders, the full videos there along
with many, many other benefits like the
podcasts, uh live sessions, detailed
research reviews, and actionable
takeaways, a vibrant community, and
more. Check it out. It's in the uh
description box. One massive effect of
omega-3s is the way that they change the
brain cell membrane. Your cell membrane
is critical for keeping your cell
integrity. It keeps things out that
aren't supposed to be in the cell, but
it also allows molecules in and it
allows molecules out. It's that last one
where omega-3s can influence brain
function. You see, your cells use
proteins called synapsins to to coil to
docking sites on the inside of the cell
membrane. Your cells need to release
communication molecules like
neurotransmitters. And the efficiency of
that release makes a huge difference on
how your neurons in your brain can
communicate with one another, creating
thought. These vesicles are equipped
with synapsins that anchor to the
skeleton of the cell called the
cytokeleton. These vesicles sit in
reserve close to the cell membrane in
case quick release is necessary. That's
called a readily releasable pool.
Omega-3s influence the production of
more of these synaps and proteins,
increasing the availability of more of
these reserve vesicles packed with
neurotransmitters to sit on the inside
of the cell ready for quick release. So
omega-3s can be transformed into ephoxes
which can influence the master protein
pam to produce more anti-inflammatory
molecules, but it can also lead to a
blocking of the NFCappa B pathway to
reduce inflammation. Beyond that,
omega-3s are believed to increase the
reserve pool of immediately available
neurotransmitters by increasing synaps
and levels that anchor these
neurotransmitter laden vesicles to the
cell skeleton. While this is all
mechanistic research and shouldn't be
used for supplementation recommendations
or changing intake, we do have clinical
evidence indicating omega-3s are a brain
benefit. So, in totality, the current
scientific evidence supports consuming
omega-3s through diet or
supplementation. But there's a breakdown
of clinical research along with a little
more on the mechanisms here. Thanks for
tuning in.